[SPEAKER_04]: So, this is Samyuttanikāya 35, 246, the simile of the lute.
[SPEAKER_04]: Bhikkhus.
[SPEAKER_04]: If for any bhikkhu or bhikkhuni, desire or passion or aversion or muddledness or resistance in regard to sights cognizable by the eye arises, they should rein their mind in from that.
[SPEAKER_04]: This path is dangerous and perilous, thorny and tangled.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a wrong turn, a bad path, a harmful way.
[SPEAKER_04]: This path is frequented by untrue persons, not by true persons.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not worthy of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Therefore, they should reign in the mind from those sights cognizable by the eye.
[SPEAKER_04]: If for any bhikkhu or bhikkhuni desire or passion or aversion or muddledness or resistance in regard to sounds cognizable by the ear,
[SPEAKER_04]: This path is dangerous and perilous, thorny and tangled.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a wrong turn, a bad path, a harmful way.
[SPEAKER_04]: This path is frequented by untrue persons, not by true persons.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not worthy of you.
[SPEAKER_04]: Therefore, they should rein in the mind from those phenomena cognizable by the mind.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suppose the crops have ripened, but the caretaker is negligent.
[SPEAKER_04]: If an ox fond of crops invades the crops, they'd indulge themselves as much as they like.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same way, an unlearned ordinary person, failing to exercise restraint in regard to the six fields of pressure, indulges themselves as much as they like and falls into carelessness in regard to the five strands of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suppose the crops have ripened and the caretaker is diligent.
[SPEAKER_04]: If an ox fond of crops invades the crops, the caretaker would grab them firmly by the muzzle.
[SPEAKER_04]: They'd grab them above the hump and hold them fast there.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, they'd give them a good thrashing before driving them away.
[SPEAKER_04]: A second time, and even a third time, the same thing might happen.
[SPEAKER_04]: As a result, no matter how long they stand or sit in a village or wilderness, that ox fond of crops would never invade that crop again, remembering the beating they got earlier.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same way, when a bhikkhu's mind is subdued, well subdued in regard to the six fields of pressure, it becomes established internally.
[SPEAKER_04]: It settles, unifies, and becomes composed.
[SPEAKER_04]: Suppose a king or their minister had never heard the sound of a lute.
[SPEAKER_04]: When he first hears the sound, he'd say, my man, what is making this sound so arousing, sensuous, intoxicating, infatuating, and captivating?
[SPEAKER_04]: They'd say to him, that, sir, is a lute.
[SPEAKER_04]: He'd say, go, my man, fetch me that lute.
[SPEAKER_04]: So they'd fetch it and say, this, sir, is that lute whose sound is so arousing, sensuous, intoxicating, infatuating, and captivating.
[SPEAKER_04]: He'd say, I'd had enough of that lute.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just fetch me the sound.
[SPEAKER_04]: They'd say, sir, this lute is made of many components assembled together, which make a sound when they're played.
[SPEAKER_04]: That is, it depends on the body, the skin, the neck, the head, the strings, the plectrum, and a person to play it properly.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's how a lute is made of many components assembled together, which make a sound when they're played.
[SPEAKER_04]: But he'd split that loot into ten pieces or a hundred pieces, then splinter it up.
[SPEAKER_04]: He'd burn the splinters with fire and reduce them to ashes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then he'd sweep away the ashes in a strong wind, or float them away down a swift stream.
[SPEAKER_04]: And he'd say, a poor thing indeed is this so-called loot, and whatever else is called a loot.
[SPEAKER_04]: But people waste their time with it, careless and duped.
[SPEAKER_04]: In the same way, a bhikkhu investigates form, as far as it goes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Feeling, as far as it goes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Perception, as far as it goes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Activities as far as they go, and consciousness as far as it goes.
[SPEAKER_04]: As he investigates them in this way, any ideas of I, or mine, or I am, do not occur to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: This is a prime example of a practice of samatha first, and vipassana later.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a prevalent notion that samatha and vipassana are two separate things, or two separate techniques, let's say, two separate types of meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, the suttas don't really support that idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, to the extent that you could argue that there is such a difference,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exemplified by this sort of practice, where somebody is concerned with directly abandoning, as it says there, passion, aversion, muddledness, resistance, desire, essentially the five hindrances in relation to the six senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the samatha aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: calming down defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, once the mind is calm, as it says there, you're then in a position to investigate more fundamental aspects of your experience, like the the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the suttas, it's said sometimes, like, some person might have a more of a tendency for vipassana, and then they should strive to attain samatha, or they have more of a tendency for samatha, and they should strive
[SPEAKER_01]: to gain vipassana, to gain insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: It literally says that, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says gain, which means it's a quality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a technique or a method.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samatha is the quality of calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Vipassana is the quality of insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're not things you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are qualities.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so,
[SPEAKER_01]: You can see that there's a very big difference between this, which is a... like, it clearly requires discernment, to some extent, to do this practice of reflecting on the danger of unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, incidentally, the only thing that the suttas teach as a method to abandon hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: There isn't a single mention of absorption method that leads you to samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: The samatha method of the suttas is contemplating the danger in the five hindrances, and that occurs like dozens of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have suttas like these, and you have suttas like those two types of thoughts, Majjhima Nikāya 19, which are basically talking about the same principle, just with like slightly different terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like this one talking about the six senses, the other one talks about the three types of thought, but fundamentally, all of it is about calming the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you calm.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you have just absorption or concentration practice, what you do is like you calm everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you imagine you have six people, and three of them committed a crime, but you throw all of them in jail.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically what's happening with the contemporary idea of a Samatha practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't actually want to see what rediversion and delusion is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just want to calm everything.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, so does that even qualify?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because are these five hindrances on that level?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the thing is, that attempt to just come everything indiscriminately, that's also driven by pre-diversion and delusion, ultimately.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, then, the states that result from that, if you read in between the lines, you see that there's still craving there, because
[SPEAKER_01]: There's mentions of, like, delighting the pleasure and, you know, indulging in the bodily sensations or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's precisely because that effort, that initial effort, that would have led to the right type of calm, to actually discern what was unwholesome from the very start.
[SPEAKER_01]: That effort was never made.
[SPEAKER_01]: People just took up a method and then did it until this result came about.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there was no discernment of
[SPEAKER_01]: What actually the five hindrances are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the suttas even say there isn't, like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, not that jhāna is explicitly samatha, but you could argue, like, sort of... standard form of samatha is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the suttas say there is no jhāna without wisdom, and there is no wisdom without jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it does talk about samatha and some other sutta as unification and as composure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's clearly moving in that same direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it says, like, even the first jhāna, if you don't understand the danger in sensuality, and you can generalize it for any unwholesome states, you won't be able to attain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how much you can absorb yourself, because you can see that that sort of contemplation, based on that danger that you understood, that's the tool you're using, like in all these suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: To calm the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, what comes from that is, when the mind is withdrawn from the hindrances, most classically described in the first jhāna formula, where it's separated from unwholesome states, then you're in a position to contemplate these things, because... not because you have, like, increased powers of observation, of, like, minute perceptions that now arise due to your absorption,
[SPEAKER_01]: But, quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you, sort of, looking at everything from a helicopter now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can look at, you can survey the territory.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it says, he examines form as far as form goes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's talking about a generality of a broader picture, not of a... not like you look at it through a microscope, and then you go back to your normal state, and what does that help you with?
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you, if you look at everything from above, as it says, separated from these things,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, eventually, when you come out, when you go back to your normal state, and you're, like, on the ground, then you have the memory of, like, you know, what you saw, and you know where to go, and you will never be able to get lost in that territory.
[SPEAKER_00]: In particularities, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, that's how practicing samatha would lead to permanent, which is just a temporary liberation, would lead to permanent liberation, even when you don't have this actual, like, bodily freedom and peace and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, an arahant wouldn't need to practice samādhi anymore, as it's said to say, it would just be a pleasant, for the sake of a pleasant abiding.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they don't need to do it anymore, if they don't want to, because they already saw, became so familiar with that territory from above, by having looked at it from above, that, yeah, they can navigate through without ever inducing ignorance, like I said, getting lost in, like, not knowing where they are, doubt and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, are there any prerequisites for getting the samatha right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can someone just, out of the blue, start reflecting on the dangers of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_02]: Like, are there ways of doing that wrong?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or can you never go wrong contemplating the danger of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which basically means that your starting point for the samatha would always be right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, definitely, it would be better to do that than to do most things people do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, of course, it would not be a genuine attempt of any kind if in your daily life you haven't abandoned sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, as it says, the prerequisite
[SPEAKER_01]: for the first jhāna is he has understood as it really is, not just intellectually or abstractly, like, you know, these things...
[SPEAKER_01]: Just an idea of all these things are not satisfactory or something that everybody can have.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has understood, as it really is, the danger in these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can ask yourself, like, yes, I'm now trying to practice meditation, but in my broader life, do I still have a plan to, like, go back to these things on a physical and verbal level?
[SPEAKER_01]: If the answer is yes, then you can be quite clear that you don't see really that danger, because you would never want to go back to something that's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: To yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you still want to go back, it's because, yeah, you might have an abstract idea of the danger, but you haven't seen it in that concrete sense that would induce that disenchantment that this talk is about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where, like, somebody tries to throw you into this charcoal pit, and you just refuse in any... you would not consent to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: And, of course, another thing is that samatha-vipassana is basically the cultivation of the seven factors of enlightenment or of awakening.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's said in the suttas that these factors are acquired with the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, eh... that's, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, Sankhya 4630, or something, or 4730?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, yeah, no, eh... yeah, no, it's 46, the Gojanga Summita Dayi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, with Venerable Dayi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, he was contemplating the... it says, like, the turning around of the five aggregates, and then he finally this... he finally acquired the seven factors of enlightenment, meaning he... like, with the right view, together with the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so that is actually not so frequently talked about, but just as one gains stream-entry or acquires the Noble Eightfold Path, these seven factors of enlightenment, or seven factors of awakening, they are exactly on that same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's just a full... it's fully synonymous, seven factors of enlightenment, with the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha in that Sutta Vidudayi also confirms that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, he says, yes, these are indeed these factors that you have now acquired,
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you then develop them, they will lead to full, complete abandonment of greed, hatred and delusion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so it's... it's... because, I mean, the first one is mindfulness, or sati, recollection.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as it's to say, there cannot be right recollection without right view, because that's what you recollect.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recollect your understanding of what craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And based on that, while you discern that craving in the experience, dhamma-vijñāya, and see, that's actually another thing that sort of ties in with how samatha cannot happen without vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like dhamma-vijñāya, you could say like distinguishing or discernment of phenomena, comes before joy and tranquility and samādhi and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you cannot distinguish
[SPEAKER_01]: In the most, in the broadest terms, like, what the problem actually is in this experience, then you will be calming down the wrong thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like I said before, you're basically calming down, like, your sense objects.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see, as I said, the simile of the cook, that discussion we previously had about the sign of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see where that attitude or that defilement is that you need to abandon.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just kind of go a roundabout way by sort of destroying the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that doesn't count, really, because it's precisely because you become accustomed to discerning what greed, aversion and delusion is, and you get that confirmation that you did actually do it properly,
[SPEAKER_01]: Out of the peace that comes from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how, then, your understanding of what these pre-division and division are becomes naturally fortified.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just get used to just abolishing everything, no matter how peaceful it is, you haven't really, like, gained any understanding of how to distinguish.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is greed from non-greed?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is aversion from non-aversion?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also not really maintainable.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you continue, you have to basically destroy the whole experience, which is impossible in the sense as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so you're just sort of replacing one thing with another, but why that
[SPEAKER_01]: What aspects were actually problematic, you never really understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, regarding the vipassana component, it's said there that it gives the simile of the lute, which doesn't mean that you see some reality that's hidden.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same thing that you had before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it says that same lute, but now you see, as it says there, its foundations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like, he focuses closer on the on the fabric of the lute, like the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The word or something, it's it's a general sort of thing that enables, like it says, enables the sound.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because initially, you're just focused on the the pleasant sound, as it says, that's gratifying, that's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't see what is the condition for this thing to be able to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, then, what you get to see with samādhi is exactly pāṭicca-saṃpāda.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get to see the dependence
[SPEAKER_01]: of everything that you could have gained any gratification or pleasure from, you see that it's dependent on this foundation that's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's a simultaneous discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like a sequence that, like, so fast
[SPEAKER_01]: That you need to catch it with this increased observation, because what... how do you know that there isn't an even faster sequence that you're not seeing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's endless, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but this is like, no, you just see the whole thing in its entirety.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, anything that you see, anything that could possibly arouse desire, is within this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, this is the extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: As far as it goes, this is what form is.
[SPEAKER_01]: As far as it goes, this is what feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so it doesn't leave anything out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that contemplation is done properly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I remember also the sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the Anguttara-Bhagavad-Gita 4, it says if somebody has samatha, but he doesn't gain the vipassana, you should find someone who can show him what is now vipassana, and then you should ask that monk, like, you know, and then it talks specifically about the conditionality of a vision phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_01]: How to examine saṅkhara, it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the vipassana there is, as you just mentioned, entirely bound up with seeing dependent origination, which is already... which equals basically having the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think it says somewhere else as well, like, samatha and vipassana pertain to true knowledge, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this is something that one should aim at establishing in one's experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we're basically saying that
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, to become a noble disciple is to gain the foundation for doing both the samatha and the vipassana rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: If that right view is not there, then that's not quite the calm that the suttas talk about when they talk about samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: And definitely, if you did gain, like, a significant degree of samatha, like, let's say, the first jhāna,
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a red flag right there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, like, as they say, even a sotāpanna would hardly have reached that point yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's like you have an even clearer, less defiled mind than a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the Buddha said, it's like a puddle that has fish in it, but then it's muddled, so you don't see actually what's inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, yours is clearer than Sotāpanna's mind, but you don't see the fish clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see the Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should really reconsider whether that's actually the right samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... and another sutta, in fact, says, again feeding into how it's this... their qualities are not things you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, when you understand the I,
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand the sights, you understand eye pressure or eye contact, you understand the feeling born of eye contact, you understand eye consciousness, and it repeats the same for the the other five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, it starts to outline the entire path.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you have that, the four right strivings are present, the four bases of power are present, the seven enlightenment factors are present, the five faculties are present, and then it mentions samatha, vipassana as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't say that he does samatha, vipassana by like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, him choosing, it's like these two things are there on account of him having this understanding beforehand of the six senses, which is another way of saying, one of the many ways of presenting what the right view is, the understanding of the six senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, really, it's more like... it's not even something you get to choose.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's more like some people could do the same contemplation
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they would be more naturally inclining towards using that contemplation to clear their mind of defilements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they might not go far enough to take it to the point of final knowledge or final insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the other hand, some other people might have more of a tendency for that clarification and clarity of phenomena, but they have a little bit too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, that results in restlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same contemplation, actually, because it doesn't... like, if you contemplate the five aggregates, it doesn't necessarily mean that you're going to be doing vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could do that also as a way of calming down the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just contemplate, well, look, I'm having these desires, I'm having these pressures here,
[SPEAKER_01]: Is this form actually mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: This form that I'm craving for?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is this feeling that I'm resisting, is it actually mine?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, did I ask this thing to arise?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you contemplate it in the five aggregates, but you only take it to the point where the the hindrances calm down, and you don't take it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's a person who, on account of what people would generally think is vipassana, is inclining more towards samatha, because it's just... it's not even something like you would be aware of
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a natural inclination that each person would have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I'm kind of doing the same practice of contemplation and mindfulness, which is the thing that binds everything together.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, in that sutta that we started out with, it says that by seeing the danger in, you know, greed, delusion, malevolence, and so on, the mind calms down, which is a samatha aspect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perhaps you can explore this a bit more now, because ordinarily, one would assume thinking about something which is dangerous would make one restless, anxious, maybe stir up the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, there can be a natural tendency to not think about that which is dangerous, because you want to gain calm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, the Buddha comes along and says the mind calms down precisely when you contemplate the danger in those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, perhaps it's worthwhile understanding why that is so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I mean, there's endless suttas about it, how that's what leads to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, so how would you go about... because it can sound to most people like it's just a sort of abstract philosophical mantra, like, oh, this is dangerous, this is dangerous, and clearly that won't do much.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it that... how is it that you contemplate the danger, let's say?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what does it mean when it says there, you rein the mind in, away from these things?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it mean, like, you completely just delete them from your awareness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is there something more to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, let's go into that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does it mean to reign in the mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, practically speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, from sense objects, which is specifically what it's talking about there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where do you go?
[SPEAKER_00]: Right?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's not that sense objects disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, can you decide to make sense objects disappear?
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be almost like disappointing your whole experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you can, but the thing is, the sutta is explicitly described.
[SPEAKER_01]: In jhāna, you walk, sit, lie down, and it says it's an escape amidst the confinement of the five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't, like, stop the five senses.
[SPEAKER_04]: Right.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I'm thinking, well, you're reeling the mind back.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, it... the fact that it says mind, you have to...
[SPEAKER_04]: Bear in mind that the mind is not the kind of the thing you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not reel your attention back.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, from looking at this thing out there, like, okay, I need to reel it back, pay attention to my nostrils.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the mind, which is already peripheral.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's what needs to be pulled back.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, that theme that you're kind of operating in, that's kind of driving your actions,
[SPEAKER_04]: That is kind of too far out, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: And you need to bring that theme back to something a bit closer, like the body, for instance, or the feeling that you're acting out of.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that is... Well, feeling is a good example, because, like, that is always going to be... like... that's always going to be part of the theme of what you're acting out on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, say your theme is just, like, total central indulgence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, so can there be an attitude of delight towards what the senses present and at the same time reigning the mind?
[SPEAKER_05]: Would that be possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is that a contradiction?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, things could be felt pleasantly, but it's different from delight, as this does talk about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by not welcoming and delighting what the senses present, then at least the mind doesn't flow in that direction, say.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's also then the opposite, which is the aversion, wanting to resist it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the attitude of not welcoming and not resisting,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is how the mind is not moving along with what the senses is doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which seems to me, which is the reigning, and it doesn't need to go that much further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because otherwise, you would be... if you go further than that, you would... you can sort of react into what the senses do, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: You go too far, so that's what I said, you neither push forward, nor do you stand still.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so... And...
[SPEAKER_01]: But then...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it that's dangerous?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it the sense objects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's always good to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is the actual danger here?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, since objects in and of themselves would be dangerous, we would basically be lost, as far as this practice goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the danger is precisely in losing one's mindfulness, and when you lose it, you will just be by default acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when that mindfulness is right, which includes... which is not a mechanical technique, but which includes... which is precisely the recollection of the danger, that's the mindfulness, which will prevent you from
[SPEAKER_00]: Acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you see a poisonous snake in the room, you're not just going to play around with it, because you put your life at risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to keep an eye on it, observe its movements, where is it, but you don't want to come too close, nor do you want to forget about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right?
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Yeah, so that's why the Buddha said the six senses... Actually, there was this one sutta where Mahārāja comes to the Buddha and says,
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: The eye, the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body, the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: A consciousness belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: The five areas belong to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything belongs to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where will you escape?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if your practice relies on just getting a different thing, even if it's just on the mental level, you're still resting on manas domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Samatha is... even samatha is like you go outside of it, temporarily, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the danger is the mental attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the problem is not that there's a trap there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The problem is that you are stepping on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point of the first jhāna, where it says you separate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You basically separate from the baits, or separate from the traps.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that they're not there, but you don't bite them anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it says the five senses are still there, but there is freedom within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's freedom within that which used to be a trap.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, further development of samatha is not like in the direction of, okay, now I absorb myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same contemplation of danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it is to say, once you've studied in the first jhāna, you reflect on the affliction in the same way you reflect on the affliction of the the five hundred siddhas in Shravasti.
[SPEAKER_01]: You reflect on the affliction of the first jhāna, which is now obviously not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's just like less pleasant than not even having that there, like the thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so you might see something beyond the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: For example, which would be the second jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, then, you know, you wouldn't even need to predetermine or know anything about what the second jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just develop the same principle in relation to this thing that you have now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you would go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you just keep doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, as to say, eventually, you would reach the cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see, even even to deepen the samatha, you still need to contemplate.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as to say that, when
[SPEAKER_01]: He says he reflects like this, and then his mind becomes established in that new dimension, quote-unquote, because that's what pulls the mind back.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's this clarity of this thing that's unwanted, and therefore the mind doesn't want anything to do with it, even though it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in another sutta, I already mentioned the one that says walking, sitting, standing during jhāna, but then there's another one that says, if a monk, his mindfulness is imperturbable, his effort is unwavering, his body is calm, his mind is composed, while walking,
[SPEAKER_01]: He's said to be diligent, ardent and resolute.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, his body is calm while walking, which for most people would seem like a contradiction, because they associate
[SPEAKER_01]: The word samatha, which, yes, could be translated as stillness, with, like, stillness of movement, but stillness of movement is not the same as calmness of mind, or, like, freedom from defilements, which is what matters, because, I think I might have mentioned that before, like, a sniper is very still when he's about to shoot someone, but that doesn't mean...
[SPEAKER_01]: But on the level of defilements, he's not actually still.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cannot equate just lack of movement with wholesomeness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's much more subtle than that, and that's why, yeah, you need to first understand what needs to be calmed down.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it says, you need to see the signs in your mind, because that's where you see what the problem is, and then you can calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, from that discussion, when we started talking about the... seeing the danger, it came across that it was just simply seeing... seeing the state of your mind, which is the extent necessary.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you go too far, and try to...
[SPEAKER_03]: I can't think of an example, but... that would be the middle.
[SPEAKER_03]: The middle ground.
[SPEAKER_03]: As soon as you start bringing that state of mind into the focus, trying to start playing with it, you've gone too far.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, is it just then... because that then reminds me of
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, what is usually not emphasized in that, is that you have a responsibility for acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where hindrances are, right?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the presence of a sensual thought or an angry thought in and of itself that constitutes a hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you going towards it or wanting to move away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what needs to be discerned and that's not... that usually doesn't get sufficient
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, it's not mentioned at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when people say, you know, like, church is awareness, or things like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but actually, you are choosing, and you cannot not choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to incorporate that dimension as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, I don't see how you can move beyond those indices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and also...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first of all, maybe you could say to Sotāpanna, just be aware, because he knows what that means.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is,
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody who hasn't understood what wholesome and unwholesome is, their idea of being aware might not be what they actually need to be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, by just mindlessly sticking to that, they would essentially omit the work that they need to do to get to stream entry.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the suttas don't say you get to stream entry by through meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: You basically get to stream entry by understanding how to meditate.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when the path begins.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you gain the seven enlightenment factors.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's more like... yeah, to some extent, you will have some... your recognition of these mental states will be improving.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're practicing the prerequisites of sense restraint, virtue, and these things, and reflecting honestly with the recognition that you still don't see the full extent of it, and if at no point you become complacent with thinking, okay, I understood now what greed, aversion, and delusion are, what the hindrances are,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's uncomfortable, but you keep the context that there's still more to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: There still has to be more to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, at some point, well, you will see the full extent of what unwholesome things are, and that's the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as you said, like, putting it into... making it into the foreground, when you're trying to discern the mental state, the thing is the mental state can never be the foreground.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: When we're talking about it theoretically, it sounds obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sure, there's the mental state and then there's the sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: But practically speaking, there will always be a tendency to confuse the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you think that the way the sense object feels is the attitude of the mind towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's a line between those two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, as the suttas say, you don't... Actually, it talks about the five senses in the first jhāna, and it says, amidst things, sights cognizable by the eye, sounds cognizable by the ear, and so on, that are likable, agreeable, pleasant, provocative of lust,
[SPEAKER_01]: There is an escape in the midst of those things, an opening amidst that confinement.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not even that you change the way that sense objects feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Other suttas would say it's like, you're dispassionate amidst that which incites passion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to then realize that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that mental state is really what needs to be... the work is in being able to draw that line between that which has arisen on its own, which is the sense object, including the way it feels, because that also belongs to Mara, as it is to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, what you're doing in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why then, as we always keep repeating, it starts with virtue, because it's on that same level of me when I see something that I want to steal with my hand, and I do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, it's not my fault that the thing presented itself as nice, as something I would like to have, but it is my responsibility if I go and take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the same principle on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not your choice at all whether the thing presents itself as agreeable, likable, etc.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your choice when you take it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's that taking up that you have to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's that taking up that you have to contemplate as dangerous, not the thing that came up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if, like, if I'm not going to steal anything, then, I mean, you can present me, like, a case of... a briefcase of two million dollars.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not dangerous in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's dangerous when I steal it and then I go to jail.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing is, you contemplate the danger and so on, but you always keep it at the back of your mind that it's highly likely that
[SPEAKER_01]: There's still more to that mental state that you still haven't seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't assume like, okay, I see now what the lust is and now it's just about contemplating the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: You exercise like...
[SPEAKER_01]: Contemplating the danger, but you always keep in mind that you may not be, at any given time, you can make the mistake of falling back into contemplating sense objects, instead of contemplating the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, as I always give the example of, like, somebody who's learning how to lift weights.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't just get focused now on piling up the weight and lifting as much as possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: They always keep in mind that, as a beginner,
[SPEAKER_01]: They can have bad form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can start making wrong movements.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, not just about, like, becoming complacent with, okay, this is how you lift the weight and now just doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always watching out for how you're doing it, why you're doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we always say, the intention is behind your actions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can be contemplating danger out of sensual reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you want some experience of release, of something like that, and then you fail to see that that is the hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're contemplating danger because you want something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't see... Because you might want something more refined and sensual.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want something outside of this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the actual thing that you should see as dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, like I said, you fall onto the level of sense objects, or you could say sense experiences, even the most subtle phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're craving for them, and then you fail to see, is the craving in relation to them?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like whether I don't have this thing now, that I think I should have.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you get the right experience, which is the right calm and everything, by not wanting.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that not wanting takes effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes discernment, it takes practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just a choiceless awareness that you relax into.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to understand what it means to not want things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, crave to understand how not to crave.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not crave for some experience that you justify as wholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: And any experience that then comes out of complete non-craving,
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like you don't even need to ask yourself whether this is wholesome, or hear it from somebody else, or you don't even need to debate, like, which is the right jhāna, which is not the right jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If there's no craving, that's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how there's the craving that brings about the end of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course, that doesn't mean you would have jhāna, eh, craving, inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, samatha is the coming of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that you have, like, craving within these...
[SPEAKER_01]: When you succeed, that's exactly when.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, but you have...
[SPEAKER_01]: But one has to start somewhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, just clarifying, because... Then, you just see exactly the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think on the level of, like, what is the right type of experience for me to have?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't consider that it doesn't matter what experience it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is that there's no craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what makes it false.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's perhaps good to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, craving does not necessarily need to be towards this or that particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: One can crave experience itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is also a form of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it says, eh... Craving is that which delights here and there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it doesn't say it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Something specific that, like, this thing is craving, and then, if you're not doing that specific thing, then you're free from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that was far more general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's anything within the six, within the all, within the six sense spaces.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you find the escape within that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it's actually a very, very lofty achievement to even reach samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like, like, you know, everybody in the Buddhist time was, was already doing that, and it's just like any...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within five days, you get it or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do a five-day meditation retreat, and from day one, people instruct you in samatha, vipassana.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's actually seriously misleading.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to say, the way to the deathless is samatha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the next, the way to the deathless, vipassana.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you could crave for understanding, if that's synonymous with the ending of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you keep in mind that, like, see, the issue with this idea of craving, or the end of craving, is that you shouldn't confuse
[SPEAKER_01]: You will have a general sort of desire to understand, and you don't give that up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you don't justify acting out of restlessness, and doubt, and like... No, you see, yes, I have this general chanda, as to say, like, interest in understanding, but you don't justify all sorts of other unwholesome states in the name of, you know, craving for the end of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, because then, that's more like just replacing one hindrance with the other.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, if you're imagining... if you have some picture of what this understanding will look like in your experience, and you're craving after that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, if you're thinking, again, in terms of like some experience that I want to get,
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you should think of it more as in how do I clarify non-craving in regard to any experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the more you understand that, the more you... it will make sense that actually it kind of doesn't make sense to pray for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But initially, you have to start with what you have, which is craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: The more you understand it, you see like it is... like nibbāna isn't something that you can pray for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not an experience in terms of like something that comes to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an attitude in relation to whatever is already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you understand it properly, that's why it says the dhamma doesn't take time.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're thinking in terms of like, oh, this thing I will get later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, you start with that, but eventually you realize like, no, if I had understood this principle from day one, there wouldn't have been anything stopping me from understanding what nibbāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would then just be a question of having a sufficiently strong mind to not fall away from that, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that, basically, nobody really starts with that kind of strong mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it takes time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the principle in itself is timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why then you would have people who would achieve arhantship in one night, others in two days, others in seven days, up to seven years.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's just the same principle, but that is timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's just a matter of like...
[SPEAKER_01]: How long it takes for the mind to become settled in it, so that it doesn't fall away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not that they were like building up this nibbāna energy or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like... understanding it, so that you don't fall away from it, even in the most... adverse circumstances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the most pressuring...
[SPEAKER_01]: challenging circumstances, that that clarity of that deathlessness, not a mystical state, but the understanding of the absence of craving, that doesn't get perturbed.
[SPEAKER_05]: There's one sutta that I remember.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not exactly, but one sutta that says, when a monk experiences a pleasant feeling, he experiences it detached.
[SPEAKER_05]: When experiencing a painful feeling, he also experiences it detached.
[SPEAKER_05]: Neither pleasant nor painful.
[SPEAKER_05]: The same.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I guess that would be that same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: The principle of samatha would be, yes, the principle of... Basically, being detached.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you experience all feelings, you experience them detached, and that's why it says... Well, it's on the basis of cultivating the force of satipaṭṭhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get to that point where you're detached from these feelings, and then you can contemplate them rightly as not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Before that, you can tell yourself that they're not yours, but...
[SPEAKER_01]: Fundamentally, the mind is still unified with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but can you be detached from feeling and then not see them as not yours?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're saying the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why then these ascetics in the Buddhist time, who did already have a development of jhāna, which wasn't a common thing, but some of them did,
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha, like Bahiya, he just told him one sentence, and then he became an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the principle of not-mindness is already implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to, like, push it one centimeter further, and then that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why it says, a bhikkhu who is in samādhi, I think that's in the first suttas of the Anguttara Nikaya Book of Tense, it says, he doesn't need to wish.
[SPEAKER_01]: May I see things as they really are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, sometimes the commentaries would describe that in order to gain insight from your samatha, you need to, like, come out of the states and then, like, the super methodical, sort of, process to it, as if you do have to be wishing for the insight to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the suttas say no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you wish for it or not,
[SPEAKER_01]: A mind who is composed sees things as they really are, because it's detached.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, seeing things from that higher view, like you're in a helicopter, you don't need to be trying to make a connection between that which you're seeing up there and that which you're seeing down there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The connection is obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also, because you wouldn't have reached that state of samatha by accident.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would have gotten there always from the starting position and having made effort to build up that clarity of these unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the connection between that which you had before and that which you have now developed, how you got to it, why it's beneficial, all that clarity would be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, there cannot be
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot happen without understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... you cannot accidentally do something hundreds of times if you didn't know that it was beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And especially because it doesn't give you an immediate result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing the right context, as it says there, contemplating that danger, it doesn't give you... you don't get a little sort of plus one.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you don't have faith, you will get carried away and you won't be able to do the right thing the necessary amount of times for you to get the confirmation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your reasoning, which is affected with ignorance and so on, will take you astray at some point.
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe it's out of topic, but maybe you have some interesting comment, because I read this letter of sister Vājīva.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it basically tells that she basically attained... attained the stream-entry, and basically she then acted, you know, pretty deranged, like...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's natural that she, like, kind of stopped her interest in the, like, particulars of the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_05]: She stopped messaging him, you know, letters and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You mean that it seems contradictory or something?
[SPEAKER_05]: Maybe contradictory, but just, you know, can you comment on it in some way that it could be such a strong experience that can be, you know, even deranging?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I wouldn't say that she got deranged.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was more like she already had these tendencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can see that she burnt the letters and stuff, and she was already getting in trouble with the other nuns, and she had to live alone, like, away from the other ones, because she just couldn't get along with the rest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like she was already like that, and then she was just restraining these tendencies out of the restlessness of wanting to understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, once she entered into the dhamma, she felt like there was no need to be restraining herself in that way anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, she just basically even disrobed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, but then...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, that's his judgment that she got the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end, that's just a... that's just a sort of estimation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, it's not necessarily like...
[SPEAKER_01]: You have also this case of this Sarakani, in the suttas, who was drinking alcohol.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, she was still keeping the eight precepts, at least, but this guy was just even... he was like an alcoholic.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people were saying, like, how can he be a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha said, well, if somebody can understand even something that was properly said, as properly said, and improperly said, as improperly said, if this tree
[SPEAKER_01]: If this tree that you see here could understand that, then I would declare him to be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean that sotāpatti is easy, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means that... Well, it's simple, but it's not easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like just being able to tell what is dhamma and what is not dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the fact that she wasn't interested in understanding more, it's just because... Like you could even see that with other lay people in the suttas who...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of interesting.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would understand the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would say that the stainless eye of the dhamma would arise, and you would expect, usually, from the point of view of somebody who still sees craving as wholesome, and doesn't see anything else, you would imagine, oh, but obviously why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why didn't he keep going?
[SPEAKER_01]: But then they would say, just like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you know, I have a lot of duties to do, so... You mean seeing cravings unwholesome, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, I'm saying, like, an ordinary person, basically, who still operates just from the point of view of craving, like, left and right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I see.
[SPEAKER_01]: They wouldn't be able to imagine how you could, like, get the right view, but then not have craving to keep going or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: All right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then... but they would just say, well, Master Gautama, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just have many duties to get care of, and they would just go back, and then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Keep the five precepts, see the monks every now and then, give offerings, but not really be striving to go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, yeah, it's... if it... that's the one of the signs that it is the real deal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you don't... like... oh, that's what to say, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the seven grains of sand compared to the to the great mountain of suffering that's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, I mean,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, sure, from the point of view of an arahant, it's not great, but especially initially, you might not feel a great sense of urgency to get rid of those seven grains of sand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only, like, you know, Sariputta and Moggallāna, who were super, sort of, eh... already had such great faculties, like, they had so much sense of urgency, that they just immediately...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, what's the next step?
[SPEAKER_01]: What's the next step?
[SPEAKER_00]: And within two weeks, they got to arhantship, so... Yeah, because if you factually know where suffering ceases, which is the understanding of the Four Noble Truths, you basically know how to not suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's just steadying your mind further in that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why also you had to... you saw the Buddha often encouraging noble disciples.
[SPEAKER_01]: He had to, like, tell them, don't become complacent, because otherwise it wouldn't quite make sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would think, like, noble disciple would be, like, this sort of... even more, sort of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Energetic and strong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Energetic and... yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, of course, they have understood what right effort is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they want to have it, they will have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they don't necessarily make the effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even monks, like, it would, it would, it would... Ānanda, like Ānanda himself, he was just distracting himself with... in that, in that case where they were in the katina, and they were just
[SPEAKER_01]: A wholesome activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's just camping together, you know, preparing the the robe for the... the Buddha's robe for the katina.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the Buddha said, like, don't... don't be negligent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Devote yourself to the practice.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, I think there are other suttas, and I think more than one.
[SPEAKER_05]: There are a couple of suttas that say that these monks, you know, get satisfied with inferior discernments, inferior distinctions, and, you know, they just stop doing anything.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because they got this distinction, they are satisfied.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, from the point of view of understanding craving, everything else has to be secondary, because everything else will be just an engagement with some sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if it's like thinking about dhamma, well, that can be affected with craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even that you wouldn't think of as a necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just see directly craving, a presence of craving, an absence of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, everything else, you see it as... See, beforehand, it would have been more like
[SPEAKER_01]: I do these things that I think will result in freedom from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then the order flips.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see the freedom from craving directly and everything you do is secondary to that understanding to now foster it and improve it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you you don't, like, hope that these things will lead to freedom from craving anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the taṅga practices, like ascetic practices, you take them with this kind of superstitious view that I will do this and then it will result in wholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: For a noble disciple, it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has the wholesome states and he sees how these things can help that further.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, which is actually exactly the same, because, I mean, if someone eats another piece of cake, it's because he believes that this piece of cake will bring him some happiness or some kind of relief from his current feeling, which is exactly the same attitude as someone that goes
[SPEAKER_02]: Or determines to never lie down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like if, again, if you do it with a with the right determination, you see the craving, and you see that this will help you not act out of it, then, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you just, like, hope that by sticking to this for who knows how many years, craving will go away by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the Buddha said there can be no wearing away of defilements without knowing and seeing what those defilements are.
[SPEAKER_05]: And actually, in suttas, these tathāngas can actually be hindrances, because it says the wilderness-dweller gets conceited, you know, that I am a wilderness-dweller and other monks are not wilderness-dwellers.
[SPEAKER_05]: I am, you know, I don't know, a eater at one city, you know, and other monks do not do that.
[SPEAKER_05]: He gets conceited.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's why then, when Devadatta wanted to make them compulsory, he said, no, let the ones who want to do it, do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that would mean that those who see, can see a craving in their minds, and they see how this helps, then they could do it without a... without a... any sense of external duty or conceit.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just a direct... And then, and see, the important thing is then, they would see that they don't have to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would be the difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, a person who still clings to virtue and duty, they would have the sense of, no, no, this is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, if, like, for some reason, they cannot do it because of some external circumstance, they would feel, like, agitated and upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which you can see, even sometimes, like, when monks
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, get sick, and then they need to go to the city or something, and then they have like this almost like sense of exasperation, because they cannot fulfill the duty that they must be always in the forest, eating rough food, and that sort of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yesterday, when we were sitting at the table, and then it came up that certain people, they don't... in discussion, maybe, they don't... they're not... they don't have the right priority, if you remember.
[SPEAKER_03]: They're not prioritizing the right thing, so then they... they go astray, or... they don't take the understanding further, or they misunderstand something.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the right priority would be putting that craving first, like switching that order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, ceasing to think that even the views that you might have, which might have actually arrived from the suttas or things like that, ceasing to assume that you're just adhering to that in and of itself, means that whatever you're doing is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start
[SPEAKER_01]: You start with those views because it's necessary to point you in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at a certain point, you need to see that the purpose of those views, if they were correct, is to show you what craving is, not to just keep building up the view in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you turn the questioning around, like the understanding that you got of, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: The background of your mind and these states that you act out of, now you see that in relation to your practice of thinking about mental states and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that now that's the level where you have to practice it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, am I acting out of doubt in relation to the right things?
[SPEAKER_01]: But before that, you certainly would have needed to some extent, like, replace your your wrong views with just... or wrong ideas with the right ideas.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at a certain point, it's like about, am I acting out of, again, yeah, craving in relation to the right thing, which makes it not right anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the most important thing to prioritize would be that sense of
[SPEAKER_01]: Always remembering that there's nothing that you can take for granted or rest on as already right before the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you cannot assume anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You cannot leave any stone unturned.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what I need to prioritize, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... Yeah, so...
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not like a sense of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, initially it feels like sort of agonizing, or that it's some sort of extreme view, that's just like as a safety mechanism, just to be extra sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no, it is... that is what sense of urgency really is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's when you recognize how deep
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignorance really goes, and that you cannot rely on any of the preconceived notions that you have, and you have to be willing to put everything, throw everything out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's again why there cannot be yoniso manasikāra without faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is to say, you will not be able to go back far enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not willing to question everything, even what you think the Buddha said and what you think the Buddha meant, because, see, even that, you do not have access to what the Buddha actually meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have is what you think the Buddha meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you always need to bear that in mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that would prevent any kind of complacency.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would see then that... you would stop chasing after some specific insight.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would just see, like, it's about... just wearing away that...
[SPEAKER_01]: Wearing away those tendencies.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, eh... there's nothing to expect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, am I wearing away the tendencies or not?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like what will happen at the end of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, what will happen at the end of it is the tendencies will wear away.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.